<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std"
     docName="draft-kampati-ipsecme-ikev2-sa-ts-payloads-opt-01"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IKEv2 Optional Child SA&amp;TS Payloads">IKEv2 Optional
    SA&amp;TS Payloads in Child Exchange</title>

    <author fullname="Sandeep Kampati" initials="S." surname="Kampati">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560066</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>sandeepkampati@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Meduri S S Bharath" initials="M." surname="Bharath">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Divyashree Techno Park, Whitefield</street>

          <city>Bangalore</city>

          <region>Karnataka</region>

          <code>560066</code>

          <country>India</country>
        </postal>

        <email>MeduriS.Bharath@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Wei Pan" initials="W." surname="Pan">
      <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei Technologies</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>101 Software Avenue, Yuhuatai District</street>

          <city>Nanjing</city>

          <region>Jiangsu</region>

          <code/>

          <country>China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>william.panwei@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <workgroup>IPSECME</workgroup>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes a method for reducing the size of the
      Internet Key Exchange version 2 (IKEv2) exchanges at time of rekeying
      IKE SAs and Child SAs by removing or making optional of SA &amp; TS
      payloads. Reducing size of IKEv2 exchanges is desirable for low power
      consumption battery powered devices. It also helps to avoid IP
      fragmentation of IKEv2 messages.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>The Internet Key Exchange protocol version 2 (IKEv2) specified in
      <xref target="RFC7296"/> is used in the IP Security (IPsec) architecture
      for the purposes of Security Association (SA) parameters negotiation and
      authenticated key exchange. The protocol uses UDP as the transport for
      its messages, which size varies from less than one hundred bytes to
      several kBytes.</t>

      <t>In 4G networks security gateways/ePDG and in 5G networks cRAN/Cloud
      will support more than 100,000 IKE/IPSEC tunnels. So on an average, for
      every second there may be hundreds or thousands of IKE SAs and Child SAs
      that are rekeying. This takes huge amount of bandwidth, packet
      fragmentation and more processing resources. And it can be solved by
      introducing the solution described in this document.</t>

      <t>This is useful in Internet of Things (IoT) devices which utilizing
      lower power consumption technology. The appendix A of <xref
      target="I-D.mglt-6lo-diet-esp-requirements"/> gives some estimate
      data.</t>

      <t>Most devices don't prefer to change cryptographic suites frequently.
      By taking this advantage the SA and TS payloads can be made optional at
      the time of rekeying IKE SAs and Child SAs. In such situation, only a
      new SPI value is needed to create the new IKE SA and Child SA. So a new
      Notify payload which contains the needed SPI value can be sent instead
      of the SA and TS payloads.</t>

      <t>In case of rekeying IKE SAs, the SA payloads can be optimized if
      there is no change of cryptographic suites. In case of rekeying Child
      SAs, the SA and TS payloads can be optimized if there is no change of
      cryptographic suites and ACL configuration.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
        when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Protocol Details">
      <t>This section provides protocol details and contains the normative
      parts.</t>

      <section title="Negotiation of Support for Optimizing Optional Payload at Rekeying IKE SAs and Child SAs">
        <t>The initiator indicates its support for optimizing optional
        payloads at rekeying IKE SAs and Child SAs by including a Notify
        payload of type MINIMAL_REKEY_SUPPORTED in the IKE_AUTH request
        message. If the responder also supports this extension, it includes
        the MINIMAL_REKEY_SUPPORTED notification in the response message. If
        the responder doesn't support this extension, it MUST ignore the
        MINIMAL_REKEY_SUPPORTED notification sent by the initiator and MUST
        NOT respond error to the initiator.</t>

        <t>The IKE_AUTH message exchange in this case is shown below:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>Initiator                         Responder
--------------------------------------------------------------------
HDR, SK {IDi, [CERT,] [CERTREQ,]
    [IDr,] AUTH, SAi2, TSi, TSr,
    N(MINIMAL_REKEY_SUPPORTED)} --&gt;
                              &lt;-- HDR, SK {IDr, [CERT,] AUTH,
                                      SAr2, TSi, TSr,
                                      N(MINIMAL_REKEY_SUPPORTED)}</artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section title="Optional Payload Optimization at Rekeying IKE SAs">
        <t>The payload optimization at rekeying IKE SAs MUST NOT be used
        unless both peers have indicated their support of this extension by
        using the negotiation method described in Section 3.1. If the
        initiator or responder decides to use this payload optimization, then
        it includes the SA_UNCHANGED notification in its CREATE_CHILD_SA
        exchange message at the time of rekeying IKE SAs. This SA_UNCHANGED
        notification MUST be included in a CREATE_CHILD_SA exchange message
        when there is no SA payloads included. The new IKE SA is created with
        the SPI value in the SA_UNCHANGED notification.</t>

        <section title="Rekeying IKE SAs When No Change of Initiator and Responder's Cryptographic Suites">
          <t>At the time of rekeying IKE SAs, the initiator MAY send the
          SA_UNCHANGED notification payload instead of the SA payloads when
          there is no change in its cryptographic suites since last
          negotiation. After receiving the initiator's request message with
          the SA_UNCHANGED notification, the responder MAY respond to the
          initiator with the SA_UNCHANGED notification payload instead of the
          SA payloads if there is also no change in its cryptographic suites
          since last negotiation.</t>

          <t>The CREATE_CHILD_SA message exchange in this case is shown
          below:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>Initiator                         Responder
--------------------------------------------------------------------
HDR, SK {N(SA_UNCHANGED), Ni, KEi} --&gt;
                              &lt;-- HDR, SK {N(SA_UNCHANGED), Nr, KEr}</artwork>
          </figure>

          <t>The initiator sends a SA_UNCHANGED notification payload, a Nonce
          payload and a Diffie-Hellman value in the KEi payload. A new
          initiator SPI is supplied in the SPI field of the SA_UNCHANGED
          notification payload.</t>

          <t>The responder replies (using the same Message ID to respond) with
          a SA_UNCHANGED notification payload, a Nonce payload and a
          Diffie-Hellman value in the KEr payload. A new responder SPI is
          supplied in the SPI field of the SA_UNCHANGED notification
          payload.</t>

          <t>When the SA_UNCHANGED notification payload is included, the SA
          payload MUST NOT be included.</t>
        </section>

        <section title="Rekeying IKE SAs When Initiator's Cryptographic Suites Changed">
          <t>At the time of or before rekeying IKE SAs, the initiator's
          cryptographic suites may be changed while there is no change of
          responder's cryptographic suites. New cryptographic suites may be
          added to the initiator, or some outdated cryptographic suites may be
          deleted from the initiator.</t>

          <t>In this situation, the initiator MUST send the SA payloads in the
          CREATE_CHILD_SA request message at the time of rekeying IKE SAs.</t>

          <t>If the responder selects a different cryptographic suite than
          which was previously negotiated, then the rekeying MUST be conducted
          in the original way defined in <xref target="RFC7296"/>, the
          responder sends the SA payloads with the selected cryptographic
          suite in the CREATE_CHILD_SA response message.</t>

          <t>If the responder selects the previously negotiated cryptographic
          suite to rekey the IKE SA, it MAY send the SA_UNCHANGED notification
          payload instead of the SA payload in the CREATE_CHILD_SA response
          message, and the initiator MUST use the cryptographic suite
          negotiated previously to create the new IKE SA. The CREATE_CHILD_SA
          message exchange in this case is shown below:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>Initiator                         Responder
--------------------------------------------------------------------
HDR, SK {SA, Ni, KEi} --&gt;
                              &lt;-- HDR, SK {N(SA_UNCHANGED), Nr, KEr}</artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Rekeying IKE SAs When Responder's Cryptographic Suites Changed">
          <t>At the time of or before rekeying IKE SAs, the responder's
          cryptographic suites may be changed while there is no change of
          initiator's cryptographic suites. New cryptographic suites may be
          added to the responder, or some outdated cryptographic suites may be
          deleted from the responder.</t>

          <t>In this situation, the initiator sends the SA_UNCHANGED
          notification payload instead of the SA payloads in the
          CREATE_CHILD_SA request message at the time of rekeying IKE SAs.</t>

          <t>If the responder decides to continue using the previously
          negotiated cryptographic suite to rekey the IKE SA, it MAY send the
          SA_UNCHANGED notification payload in the CREATE_CHILD_SA response
          message, then the rekeying is conducted like Section 3.2.1.</t>

          <t>If the responder decides to re-negotiate the cryptographic suite,
          it MUST send NO_PROPOSAL_CHOSEN notification payload in the
          CREATE_CHILD_SA response message. After receiving this error
          notification, the initiator MUST retry the CREATE_CHILD_SA exchange
          with the SA payloads. Then the rekeying is conducted in the original
          way defined in <xref target="RFC7296"/>. The CREATE_CHILD_SA message
          exchange in this case is shown below:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>Initiator                         Responder
--------------------------------------------------------------------
HDR, SK {N(SA_UNCHANGED), Ni, KEi} --&gt;
                              &lt;-- HDR, SK {N(NO_PROPOSAL_CHOSEN),
                                      Nr, KEr}
HDR, SK {SA, Ni, KEi} --&gt;
                              &lt;-- HDR, SK {SA, Ni, KEi}</artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section title="Optional Payload Optimization at Rekeying Child SAs">
        <t>The payload optimization at rekeying Child SAs MUST NOT be used
        unless both peers have indicated their support of this extension by
        using the negotiation method described in Section 3.1. If the
        initiator or responder decides to use this payload optimization, then
        it includes the SA_TS_UNCHANGED notification in its CREATE_CHILD_SA
        exchange message at the time of rekeying Child SAs. This
        SA_TS_UNCHANGED notification MUST be included in a CREATE_CHILD_SA
        exchange message when there is no SA and TS payloads included. The new
        Child SA is created with the SPI value in the SA_TS_UNCHANGED
        notification.</t>

        <section title="Rekeying Child SAs When No Change of Initiator and Responder's Cryptographic Suites and ACL Configuration">
          <t>At the time of rekeying Child SAs, the initiator MAY send the
          SA_TS_UNCHANGED notification payload instead of the SA and TS
          payloads when there is no change in its cryptographic suites and ACL
          configuration since last negotiation. After receiving the
          initiator's request message with the SA_TS_UNCHANGED notification,
          the responder MAY respond to the initiator with the SA_TS_UNCHANGED
          notification payload instead of the SA and TS payloads if there is
          also no change in its cryptographic suites and ACL configuration
          since last negotiation.</t>

          <t>The CREATE_CHILD_SA message exchange in this case is shown
          below:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>Initiator                         Responder
--------------------------------------------------------------------
HDR, SK {N(REKEY_SA), N(SA_TS_UNCHANGED),
    Ni, [KEi,]} --&gt;
                              &lt;-- HDR, SK {N(SA_TS_UNCHANGED),
                                      Nr, [KEr,]}</artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Rekeying Child SAs When Initiator's Cryptographic Suites or ACL Configuration Changed">
          <t>At the time of or before rekeying Child SAs, the initiator's
          cryptographic suites or ACL configuration may be changed while there
          is no change of responder's cryptographic suites and ACL
          configuration.</t>

          <t>In this situation, the initiator MUST send the SA and TS payloads
          in the CREATE_CHILD_SA request message at the time of rekeying Child
          SAs.</t>

          <t>If the responder selects a different cryptographic suite or
          different Traffic Selectors than which were previously negotiated,
          then the rekeying MUST be conducted in the original way defined in
          <xref target="RFC7296"/>, the responder sends the SA payloads with
          the selected cryptographic suite and the TS payloads in the
          CREATE_CHILD_SA response message.</t>

          <t>If the responder selects the previously negotiated cryptographic
          suite and Traffic Selectors to rekey the Child SA, it MAY send the
          SA_TS_UNCHANGED notification payload instead of the SA and TS
          payloads in the CREATE_CHILD_SA response message, and the initiator
          MUST use the cryptographic suite and Traffic Selectors negotiated
          previously to create the new Child SA. The CREATE_CHILD_SA message
          exchange in this case is shown below:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>Initiator                         Responder
--------------------------------------------------------------------
HDR, SK {N(REKEY_SA), SA, Ni, [KEi,]
    TSi, TSr}   --&gt;
                              &lt;-- HDR, SK {N(SA_TS_UNCHANGED),
                                      Nr, KEr}</artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section title="Rekeying Child SAs When Responder's Cryptographic Suites or ACL Configuration Changed">
          <t>At the time of or before rekeying Child SAs, the responder's
          cryptographic suites or ACL configuration may be changed while there
          is no change of initiator's cryptographic suites and ACL
          configuration.</t>

          <t>In this situation, the initiator MAY send the SA_TS_UNCHANGED
          notification payload instead of the SA and TS payloads in the
          CREATE_CHILD_SA request message at the time of rekeying Child
          SAs.</t>

          <t>If the responder decides to continue using the previously
          negotiated cryptographic suite and Traffic Selectors to rekey the
          Child SA, it MAY send the SA_TS_UNCHANGED notification payload in
          the CREATE_CHILD_SA response message, then the rekeying is conducted
          like Section 3.3.1.</t>

          <t>If the responder decides to re-negotiate the cryptographic suite
          or Traffic Selectors, it MUST send NO_PROPOSAL_CHOSEN notification
          payload in the CREATE_CHILD_SA response message. After receiving
          this error notification, the initiator MUST retry the
          CREATE_CHILD_SA exchange with the SA and TS payloads. Then the
          rekeying is conducted in the original way defined in <xref
          target="RFC7296"/>. The CREATE_CHILD_SA message exchange in this
          case is shown below:</t>

          <figure>
            <artwork>Initiator                         Responder
--------------------------------------------------------------------
HDR, SK {N(SA_TS_UNCHANGED), Ni, KEi} --&gt;
                              &lt;-- HDR, SK {N(NO_PROPOSAL_CHOSEN),
                                      Nr, KEr}
HDR, SK {N(REKEY_SA), SA, Ni, [KEi,]
    TSi, TSr}   --&gt;
                             &lt;--  HDR, SK {SA, Nr, [KEr,]
                                      TSi, TSr}</artwork>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Payload Formats">
      <section title="MINIMAL_REKEY_SUPPORTED Notification">
        <t>The MINIMAL_REKEY_SUPPORTED notification is used by the initiator
        and responder to inform their ability of optimizing optional payload
        at the time of rekeying IKE SAs and Child SAs to the peers. It is
        formatted as follows:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork>                     1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Next Payload  |C|  RESERVED   |         Payload Length        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Protocol ID(=0)| SPI Size (=0) |      Notify Message Type      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Protocol ID (1 octet) - MUST be 0.</t>

            <t>SPI Size (1 octet) - MUST be 0, meaning no SPI is present.</t>

            <t>Notify Message Type (2 octets) - MUST be &lt;Need to get value
            from IANA&gt;, the value assigned for the MINIMAL_REKEY_SUPPORTED
            notification.</t>
          </list>This notification contains no data.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="SA_UNCHANGED Notification">
        <t>The SA_UNCHANGED notification is used to replace the SA payloads at
        the time of rekeying IKE SAs when there is no change of cryptographic
        suites in initiator or responder. It is formatted as follows:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork> 0                 1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Next Payload  |C|  RESERVED   |         Payload Length        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Protocol ID    | SPI Size (=8) |      Notify Message Type      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                Security Parameter Index (SPI)                 |
|                                                               |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Protocol ID (1 octet) - MUST be 1.</t>

            <t>SPI Size (1 octet) - MUST be 8.</t>

            <t>Notify Message Type (2 octets) - MUST be &lt;Need to get value
            from IANA&gt;, the value assigned for the SA_UNCHANGED
            notification.</t>

            <t>SPI (8 octets) - Security Parameter Index. The initiator sends
            initiator SPI. The responder sends responder SPI.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="SA_TS_UNCHANGED Notification">
        <t>The SA_TS_UNCHANGED notification is used to replace the SA payloads
        and TS payloads at the time of rekeying Child SAs when there is no
        change of cryptographic suites and ACL configuration in initiator or
        responder. It is formatted as follows:</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork> 0                 1                   2                   3
 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
| Next Payload  |C|  RESERVED   |         Payload Length        |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|Protocol ID    | SPI Size (=4) |      Notify Message Type      |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
|                Security Parameter Index (SPI)                 |
+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+</artwork>
        </figure>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>Protocol ID (1 octet) - MUST be either (2) to indicate AH or
            (3) to indicate ESP.</t>

            <t>SPI Size (1 octet) - MUST be 4.</t>

            <t>Notify Message Type (2 octets) - MUST be &lt;Need to get value
            from IANA&gt;, the value assigned for the SA_TS_UNCHANGED
            notification.</t>

            <t>SPI (4 octets) - Security Parameter Index. The initiator sends
            initiator SPI. The responder sends responder SPI.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document defines two new Notify Message Types in the "IKEv2
      Notify Message Types - Status Types" registry. IANA is requested to
      assign codepoints in this registry.</t>

      <figure>
        <artwork>NOTIFY messages: status types            Value
----------------------------------------------------------
MINIMAL_REKEY_SUPPORTED                  TBD
SA_UNCHANGED                             TBD
SA_TS_UNCHANGED                          TBD</artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TBD</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7296"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8174'?>

      <?rfc ?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.mglt-6lo-diet-esp-requirements'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
